Finding Aid for the Albert Hay Malotte Papers PASC-M.0040
UCLA Library Special Collections
Albert Hay Malotte papers
1945-1960
UCLA Library Special Collections
Malotte, Albert Hay
PASC-M.0040
0.6 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Albert Hay Malotte (1895-1964) was most well known as a songwriter and composer. Some of his more popular works include scores for Academy Award-winning Walt Disney animation shorts Ferdinand the Bull (1938) and The Ugly Duckling (1939) and a musical setting of The Lord's Prayer (1935). During the 1940s and 1950s, Malotte wrote scores for comedic musical plays, some of which are included in this collection. Scores and written scripts for the musicals Fanfare, Limbo (also known as Once upon a Dream), The Big Tree (later renamed California Story), and Lo'loma make up the bulk of the materials, but an autographed photograph of Malotte and sheet music for his song I am Proud to be an American, are also included.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9922211143606533
Biographical Note
Albert Hay Malotte was born May 19, 1895 in Philadelphia, PA. Malotte developed an interest in music at an early age and was a choir boy at Saint James Episcopal Church (Philadelphia) under the direction of his father, Charles Malotte, who served as a choirmaster there. Later in life, Malotte studied under Victor Herbert, a composer and founder of the American Society of Composers, Authors, and Publishers (ASCAP). He received further training in organ, voice, and composition abroad and worked as a concert organist for several years. His interest in the American West eventually took him to Hollywood, CA, where he worked for Walt Disney Studios. While at Disney, Malotte composed the scores for several of the company's Silly Symphonies, including the Academy Award-winning Ferdinand the Bull (1938) and The Ugly Duckling (1939). Malotte's most popular work was a musical setting of The Lord's Prayer (1935), but he also wrote numerous songs and composed multiple movie and musical scores during the course of his career. In addition to scoring musicals written by others, Malotte wrote and scored his own musical, Lo'loma, in the early 1950s. Lo'loma tells the story of Sergeant Eddie Kwaihoya, a Hopi man who returns to his village in Arizona to marry his sweetheart after serving as a Marine in World War II. Albert Hay Malotte died on November 16, 1964 in Los Angeles, CA.
Scope and Content
This collection is chiefly comprised of musical plays scored by Albert Hay Malotte during the 1940s and 1950s. Copies of musical scores and written scripts for the comedic plays Fanfare, Limbo (also known as Once upon a Dream), The Big Tree (later renamed California Story), and Lo'loma make up the bulk of the materials. Noted collaborators on these works include Rowland V. Lee and Irving Phillips, who authored the lyrics and dialogue of most of these musicals, with the exception of Lo'loma, which was written and scored by Malotte. An autographed photograph of Albert Hay Malotte and sheet music for the song I am Proud to be an American (1960) are also included in the collection.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series: Series 1: Lo'loma, 1953-1954 Series 2: Musical scores and scripts, 1945-1950 Subseries 2.1: Fanfare, 1945-1946 Subseries 2.2: Limbo, 1947-1950 Subseries 2.3: The Big Tree, 1949 Series 3: Sheet music, 1960
Musicals—Writing and publishing; Musicals—Scores
- Series 1: Lo'loma, 1953-1954
  Scope and Contents
  Includes the musical score, script, and promotional materials for Albert Hay Malotte's musical, Lo'loma. Unlike the other musicals in this collection, Malotte both wrote and scored Lo'loma. The musical tells the story of Sergeant Eddie Kwaihoya, a Hopi man who returns to his village in Arizona to marry his sweetheart after serving as a Marine in World War II. It debuted in Phoenix, AZ in 1953 and received positive reviews, some of which are included in the collection. Other promotional materials include an autographed photograph of Malotte, as well as a program from the musical's debut performance.
  Arrangement
  Materials are arranged in roughly chronological order.
  - Lo'loma (script), 1953 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Songs from Lo'loma (score), 1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Promotional materials (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series 2: Musical scores and scripts, 1945-1950
  Contains scripts and musical scores for the comedic musical plays Fanfare (1945-1946), Limbo (1947-1950; also known as One upon a Dream), and The Big Tree (1949; later renamed California Story). Rowland Vance Lee (Rowland V. Lee) is credited as the author of the script and lyrics for both Fanfare and The Big Tree; Irving Phillips is credited as the author of the script and lyrics for Limbo. Albert Hay Malotte composed the scores for all three works.
  - Fanfare, 1945-1946
    - Fanfare (score), 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Fanfare (script), ca. 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Limbo, 1947-1950
    - Limbo (score), 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Limbo (script), 1950 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - The Big Tree, 1949
    - The Big Tree (score), 1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Big Tree (script), 1949 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series 3: Sheet music, 1960
  Sheet music (2 pages) for the song I am Proud to be an American, written and scored by Albert Hay Malotte.
  - I am Proud to be an American, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 6)